<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jake Parker&#39;s personal site</title>
    <description>Jake Parker is a synthetic biologist interested in the forces which shape  molecular evolution, and harnessing that understanding to build new molecules.  This site is for thoughts on computational biology, (bio)informatics, synthetic  biology, biotech startups, innovation and entrepreneurship. 
</description>
    <link>http://jakeparker.xyz/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jakeparker.xyz/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 21:20:23 +1000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 21:20:23 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Jekyll!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;Tom&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints &#39;Hi, Tom&#39; to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 18:32:01 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://jakeparker.xyz/jekyll/update/2017/07/29/welcome-to-jekyll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jakeparker.xyz/jekyll/update/2017/07/29/welcome-to-jekyll.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fluidity of organisms</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;fluidity-of-organisms&quot;&gt;fluidity of organisms&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;## Or, why taxonomy is doomed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxonomy- no, not the study of accountants-&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; is the study of classification. Taxonomy is the business of organising the world into neat little groups and sub-groups. We do it to everything from music (which genre?) to land (which continent?&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;). This is especially true in the natural sciences where the human condition of organisation has revealed stark patterns in nature. These observations, in turn, have led to hypothesies, predicitons, and subsequently- to complete the cycle- new systems of classification. The case in point is that of biological taxonomy, which led to one of the greatest scientific insights of all modern human history: relation through decent with modification, or, the theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;darwins-great-insight-everythings-related-literally&quot;&gt;Darwin’s great insight: everything’s related, literally.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darwin’s job on the HMS Beagle was to catelogue. He was to record and collect all the new forms of life he discovered while travelling to exotic places and bring them back for European eyes. But the trip provided Darwin with more species to look at, it gave him a fresh landscape upon which to look. While he could have realised what he did in his arm-chair back home, it was the Gallapigous finches which triggered his leap. Group: animals, group: birds, group: finches, group: island-finches, Darwin’s great insight was that these were connected vertically. That island finches were more similar to each other than a bird is to a bear not because God or Nature designed them that way, but because they had at one stage &lt;em&gt;been the same thing&lt;/em&gt;. More importantly, he propposed the way that this could happen naturally, given the passage of time: decent with modification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around the same time, Mendel was doing his now famous- then virtually unknown- work on heritable traits. The combination of these two ideas along with the discovery of the material responsible for encoding all that information and the mechanism of modification, has led to the Modern evolutionary synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Molecular understanding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-modernity, genomic or architectural synthesis
We now have a fairly good understanding of the bricks used in biology, or, at least, what kinds of bricks exist.
The next step is to get a better understanding of the interconnectedness of those components, in terms of networks, regulation and evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our ability to investigate these connections have been driven by the large scale data we are now able to produce and process from the so-called “omics” platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These data are consistently showing that there is no such thing as a closed system.  For our understanding of humans, in particular, the implication is clear; we are not a ship carrying a few stowaways, we and the stow-aways are the ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-exactly-is-an-organism&quot;&gt;So, what exactly is “an organism”?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physical - issues: 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ship_of_Theseus&quot;&gt;ship of theseus&lt;/a&gt; 
we’re not just one set of cells! On average the ratio of human to non-human cells might be flipped depending on how recently we went to the toilet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;degree of integration
physical cutoff?
fungi, coral, jellyfish
genetic cutoff?
organelles
dependence?
flowering plants
parasites
viruses
We have to acknowledge the gene-centric model of evolution. Organisms exist because cooperation between individual self-replicating units proved to be a good way of surviving and replicating. However, just as Foucault dismissed the old concepts of simple hierarchical structures in human affairs and proposed his own concepts of a complex web of power, so too must we reconsider our ideas about genes and organisms. Every conceivable type of interaction with benefit to at least one element will be found in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything starts out as one cell and grows from there, right? In that original cell there is one “set” of DNA which might be anything from a single circular structure to multiple chromosomes and assorted plastids. Let’s just call whatever develops from that, in isolation, an organism. The problem is that nothing develops “in isolation” there will always be environmental influences, varying from subtle to extreme. For example, during mammalian development the foetus is influenced by its mother in a number of ways including through nutrition, hormones, immune response and microbial communities. This has interesting implications for any &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De-extinction&quot;&gt;plans to bring animals back from extinction&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metabolic
Define environmental&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-constraints-of-evolution&quot;&gt;The constraints of evolution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;life as a network of interacting molecular species
define a closed system
whole world?
environmental niche
clusters within that system 
eg organisms
sub-clusters within that
eg environmental niches
gut of termite
systems are very quickly limited in their ability to innovate as network effects result in co-dependencies
these constraints exist within molecules (amino acid-amino acid); between molecules (metabolites, proteins, nucleic acids); between cells (self-self, tissue-tissue, self-nonself); and, between organisms.
figs/fig-wasps
flowering plants and pollinators
rubisco
this means that multi-cellular organisms, which are almost never of uniform genetic composition, are very quickly irreversibly entangled
old friend’s theory
impact of co-evolution with viruses
alternate concepts
holocene
define an “organism” by a set of metabolic genes
networks
essentially a clustering problem
there will never be a single “correct” answer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-do-we-perform-taxonomy-after-all&quot;&gt;Why do we perform taxonomy after all?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taxonomy is, like all intellectual endevours, persued because it’s of conceptual ease for us, humans. All ideas and theories are just models to help us comprehend the world so we don’t need an absolute, technically perfect system- just the best model for the job. The important thing is that we’re conscious of the assumptions which are implicit in the model so we can move beyond it when we discover a deficiency and derive a deeper understanding of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] While tax and taxonomy both derive from greek roots, the tax in taxonomy comes from “taxis” for arrangement while tax comes from “tassein” meaning to fix.
[2] Geographic or socio-political!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;```python&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;```&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2017 18:32:01 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://jakeparker.xyz/biology,/taxonomy,/averages/2017/07/26/the-fluidity-of-organims.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jakeparker.xyz/biology,/taxonomy,/averages/2017/07/26/the-fluidity-of-organims.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>biology,</category>
        
        <category>taxonomy,</category>
        
        <category>averages</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
